Guide to Maria Irene Fornés Papers MSS 413
Fales Library and Special Collections
- Series II: Notes, Scenarios, and Writings in Process, 1980s-1990s, undated; 2.75 linear feet in 4.75 document boxes.
  - Miscellaneous Short Notes, undated (Box 20, Folder 27-29, Box 21, Folder 1-6, Box 22, Folder 1-5)
- Series III: Business and Finance Files, 1971-2004; 1.5 linear feet in 3 document boxes.
  This series contains documents pertaining to Fornés’ professional activities, business, and finances, as well as some materials on her personal business and finances. These include correspondence concerning productions of her plays, requests to stage her works, project and grant proposals, contracts, statements from her agent, pay stubs, calendars, schedules, itineraries, property tax and income records, invoices for maintenance fees for her New York City condominium and for renovations to her home in Delaware County, New York.
  - Actor/Director/Set Designer Photographs and Resumes, undated (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Addresses and Telephone Numbers, undated (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Calendars and Schedules, 2003, undated (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Contracts, 1988-2002, undated (Box 23, Folder 4-5)
  - Correspondence--A-I, 1987-2003 (Box 23, Folder 6-15)
  - Correspondence--J-Z, 1976-2004 (Box 24, Folder 1-16)
  - Dramatists Guild of America Resource Directories, 1990s (Box 24, Folder 17)
  - Four-Gated City Film Project--Proposal and Correspondence, circa 1975-1976 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Memorabilia for Theater Seasons, 1991-1998, undated (Box 25, Folder 2-6)
  - Mudra Theatre Workshop, 1973 (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - Personal Finances, 1985-2004, undated (Box 25, Folder 8-9)
  - Soccoro--Film Proposal (Partial Draft), circa 1971 (Box 25, Folder 10)
- Series IV: INTAR (International Arts Relations, Inc.) Records, 1992-2000; 0.25 linear feet in 1 document box.
  Materials in this series document administrative and internal workings of one of the oldest Latino theater companies in the United States, through memos, budgets, production schedules and cast lists for INTAR productions. Fornés had a long association with the organization in a number of capacities, most notably as director and teacher of its playwrights-in-residence program.
  - 1992-2000 Seasons (Box 26, Folder 1-7)
- Series V: Family Papers, 1947-1980s; 0.1 linear feet in 2 folders.
  This series contains government documents and applications for government assistance, and documents and correspondence concerning emigration from Cuba and immigration to the United States, including Irene Fornés’ naturalization certificate. Also included are affidavits and requests by Fornés and members of her extended family to Cuban and U.S. authorities to facilitate emigration of relatives in Cuba to the United States. In addition, there are applications by Fornés’ mother, Carmen Collado Fornés for public housing and her food stamp identification cards. Nongovernmental official documents such as a travel identification card for American Youth Hostels, Inc. are also part of the series.
  - Emigration, Immigration, and Other Documents, 1947-2000, undated (Box 26, Folder 8-9)
- Series VI: Personal Correspondence, 1909-2004; 0.25 linear feet in 1 document box. (Box 27, Folder 1-5)
  This series contains letters and cards from Irene Fornés’ family and photocopies of same, and letters between Fornés and her friends and family. These include some of the letters that Fornés drew upon as sources for two of her plays. Family correspondents in this series include Carmen Collado Fornés, Ramon Collado, Rafael Fornés, and "Pepe."
  - Family, 1909-2004 (Box 27, Folder 1-4)
  - Friends, 1996-2004, undated (Box 27, Folder 5)
- Series VII: Teaching Materials and Students’ Work, 1971-2001; 1.25 linear feet in 3 document boxes.
  This series consists of students’ handwritten, typewritten, or mimeographed scenarios; scripts for plays and playlets; stories; and poems. In addition, the series includes flyers, correspondence, exercise instructions, participant lists, play notes, and drawings that pertain to, or that arose from, Irene Fornés’ teaching and playwriting workshops. She briefly taught elementary school students, but the bulk of her students were college students and adults who were emerging playwrights. Because Fornés’ method for teaching plays included close collaboration, a number of these scripts were co-written by several different students as well as with Fornés herself ( Meche is one clear example). In addition to those who received formal instruction from Fornés through workshops, lectures or classes, the series also includes materials from informal “students” of hers who may never have been enrolled in any of the courses she taught--aspiring playwrights whom she seems to have mentored or for whose work she seems to have provided criticism.
  - Colloquia and Speaking Engagements, 1993-1994, 2002, undated (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Davidson College, 1991-1992, 2001 (Box 28, Folder 2-3)
  - [From a Writers in the Schools Program]--Student Writings, Teachers and Writers Collaborative, 1971-1972 (Box 28, Folder 4-10)
  - INTAR Hispanic Playwrights in Residence Laboratory, 1982-1983 (Box 28, Folder 11-15)
  - Miscellaneous Student Work, Assignment Outlines, Course Evaluations, undated (Box 28, Folder 16)
    Includes a story by American writer Harriet Sohmers Zwerling.
  - "Recommendations for My Students" (Handwritten Drafts), undated (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - Students' Plays--Scripts and Notes, 1981-2005, undated (Box 29, Folder 2-6, Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Unidentified Play--Scripts, Partial Script, and Script Fragments (Possibly by Students), 2003-2004, undated (Box 30, Folder 2-3)
  - Workshops, 1982-2003 (Box 30, Folder 4-11)
- Series VIII: Subject/Research Files, 1957-2000s; 3.5 linear feet in 7 document boxes and 1 computer file.
  This series includes a wide-ranging collection of materials gathered as research for Fornés’ plays on subjects as varied as fortune-telling, President John F. Kennedy’s assassination, Fidel Castro, and silent films, as well as articles documenting Fornés’ career and the reception of her plays, her interests in drama and art, and her extensive travels, as well as those of her mother. Items include biographical portraits and transcripts of interviews with Fornés; newspaper and magazine clippings; play and book reviews; programs and announcements for, and invitations to, plays, dances, musical performances, art exhibits and openings; maps and travel ephemera; catalogs; posters; photographs; song lyrics; and recipes. Most of those materials originally received in labeled folders have retained their original folder titles (indicated by by quotation marks).
  - "American Songs", undated (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Artists-in-Residence Fellowships, 1992, 2001-2004 (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - Balseros ("Rafters"), 1994, undated (Box 31, Folder 3)
  - Booklets and Pamphlets, 1928, 1994-2001, undated (Box 31, Folder 4)
  - "Canciones Cubanas", 1980, 1997, undated (Box 31, Folder 5)
  - Catalogs, 2003-2004, undated (Box 31, Folder 6)
  - [Cooking] "Recipes", undated (Box 31, Folder 7)
  - Directing, undated (Box 31, Folder 8)
  - Ephemera and Artifacts, undated (Box 31, Folder 9)
  - Fornés, Carmen--Travel, 1961, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 33, Folder 1, Box 32, Folder 1-5)
  - Fornés, Maria Irene--Awards, Honors, and Fellowships, 1966-2003, undated (Box 33, Folder 2)
  - Fornés, Maria Irene--Biographical, 1966-2003, undated (Box 33, Folder 3-6)
  - Fornés, Maria Irene--Genealogical Information, undated (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - Fornés, Maria Irene--MacDowell Colony, 1964 (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - Fornés, Maria Irene--Others' Plays Directed by Fornés--Reviews, 1986, 1990-1995, undated (Box 34, Folder 4)
  - Fornés, Maria Irene--Panels and Symposia, 1993-2002 (Box 34, Folder 5)
  - Fornés, Maria Irene--Photographs of Fornés, Family and Friends, undated (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - Fornés, Maria Irene--Playbills, Programs, Announcements, and Listings, 1963-2002, undated (Box 34, Folder 6-7)
  - Fornés, Maria Irene--Plays--Reviews, 1969-2000, undated (Box 34, Folder 8-9, Box 35, Folder 1)
  - Fornes, Maria Irene--Posters--Readings and Festivals, 1993-1997 (Map-case 2.C, Folder 11)
  - Fornés, Maria Irene--Published Works By and Books About--Reviews, 1999-2002, undated (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - Fornés, Maria Irene--Resume, 1993; FA_MSS_413_ER_5; 31.38 kilobytes in 1 computer file. (Item ER 5)
    31.38 Kilobytes (1 computer file).
  - Fornés, Maria Irene--Travel, 1957, 1963 (Box 35, Folder 3-4)
  - Fornés, Maria Irene--Undergraduate(?) Thesis on Work of, 1997 (Box 35, Folder 5)
  - "Fortune Telling", undated (Box 35, Folder 6)
  - "Japanese Noh Drama", undated (Box 35, Folder 7)
  - "Juanita Castro", 1964 (Box 35, Folder 8)
  - Magazines, 1985, 1994-2004 (Box 35, Folder 9-10)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings, 1937, 1979-2005, undated (Box 36, Folder 1-3)
  - Newspapers, 1989, 2001 (Box 36, Folder 4)
  - Organizations, 1989-2004, undated (Box 36, Folder 5)
  - "Pictures", 1996-2002, undated (Box 36, Folder 6)
  - Plays by Others--Announcements, Programs, and Reviews, 1975-2004, undated (Box 36, Folder 7, Box 37, Folder 1)
  - Plays by Others--Scripts, undated (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - "President John F. Kennedy"--Assassination, 1963 (Map-case 2.C, Folder 11)
  - "President John F. Kennedy"--Assassination, Life, 1963-1966 (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - Songs, 1919, 1934, undated (Box 37, Folder 4)
  - Spanish-American War, 1998, undated (Box 37, Folder 5)
  - Tango, 1986, 2000, undated (Box 37, Folder 6)
  - Teaching Writing, 2001-2002, undated (Box 37, Folder 7)
  - Travel--Europe, 1990, 1994, undated (Box 37, Folder 8-9)